This is a frustrating video to make, but
I've been meaning to make it for quite
some time. So, I'm plowing forward. In
the end, I'm going to infect you with
that same frustration, but I can tell
you that we'll still come out the other
end with actionable understanding on
one, why low-carbohydrate diets raise
the risk of premature death,
two, why it may not matter for many, and
three, how to avoid it altogether while
still sticking to a low-carb diet. All
based on these studies including
hundreds of thousands of people.
I realize that when you pair a low-carb
diet raises the risk of premature death
and
why it won't matter, that's a weird
combination. Yeah, man,
I don't really care if I die years
earlier than I'm supposed to.
Anyway, bear with me. I'll explain. So,
I analyzed five studies, some of them
individual studies and one meta-analysis
trying to find out if across hundreds of
thousands of participants in some of
these there is an increased risk of
dying on a low-carbohydrate diet
compared to generally a
high-carbohydrate diet. Now, there's
plenty of definitions for what low-carb
and high-carb are and we'll get into
what that means, but let me give you a
brief overview of the results of these
analyses. These analyses indicate
reduced risk of premature death when
people consume a low-carbohydrate diet
and these indicate there is raised risk
of premature death like we see here
where we're looking at death rates over
time. The higher the lines go, the more
death and each line corresponds to a
certain amount of carbohydrate
consumption. The purple line there, the
Q4, is the lowest carbohydrate
condition, clearly indicating increased
risk of death.
How do we square all that mixed
information? Why don't studies agree?
Before someone screams funding, I
provide all the funding and conflicts of
interest information attached to this
video. Many of the studies were publicly
funded with no conflicts of interest,
but there's still plenty of good
explanation for why these studies
disagree and how we can apply this
information regardless. For one, a
low-carbohydrate diet can be healthy or
unhealthy, which one analysis delved
into. Essentially, they broke up 37,000
people's data into two buckets, healthy
or unhealthy. We'll get into what that
means momentarily. When looking at
people that were on a lower-carbohydrate
diet, yes, the diet was made up of
unhealthy ingredients, there was a
consistent increase in mortality risk.
However, when the low-carbohydrate diet
was made up of healthy ingredients, the
reverse happened. People had reduced
risk. So, this could be an easy defining
feature because if studies don't make
that distinction, it could mean that the
data skewed toward harm or no risk
reduction. That being the case, what
qualified for each bucket as healthy or
unhealthy? The unhealthy was qualified
as high in saturated fat, animal
protein, and a lack of healthy
carbohydrates like fiber and
nutrient-dense foods like fruits and
non-starchy vegetables. The healthy was
defined as, well, the opposite, higher
in unsaturated fats, plant protein
sources, and reduced consumption of
low-quality carbohydrates like added
sugars and refined grains.
Now, that might sound pretty
straightforward, but there are also
analyses indicating that animal protein
can lead to reduced mortality. In fact,
a clear illustration of that is here. If
the lines had dropped below one on the
vertical axis there, that means that
there's reduced mortality risk and we're
looking at increasing amounts of animal
protein and fat on the horizontal axis.
Clearly, a little and even a moderate
amount of animal protein indicates
reduced mortality risk, which then
rebounds back up losing the benefit at
higher consumption. So, how do we square
that? One analysis indicates increased
risk of death and the other says, "Whoa
there, buddy. It might be
dose-dependent. Some is good, too much
is bad." Keep in mind that this is all
done after adjusting for potential other
factors like these. Well, while a lot of
that mix-up is echoed in other studies,
most only break out total protein and
also indicate increased mortality risk,
but there is one study that I think is
better in a few different ways and gives
us far clearer answers, and that's this
one. This one actually echoes what the
others mostly say, but it addresses some
methodological issues that I won't bore
you with unless you're a Physionic
Insider. In that analysis, the
researchers compared more
vegetable-heavy versus animal-based
food-heavy low-carbohydrate diets and
showed the same result that less
animal-based proteins and fat
consumption, but more vegetable
consumption related to greater
protection from mortality. But, here's
the kicker, in none of their group study
did people eat no animal protein and
fat. So, there was a protective
relationship of consuming some while
prioritizing vegetable consumption. The
bottom line is that in most of these
studies, eating a small or to even a
moderate amount of animal protein and
fats on a lower-carbohydrate diet was
related to reduced mortality risk if
accompanied by an emphasis on vegetables
and other plant-based sources as well.
I'll dive deeper into the details in
just a minute. Now, there is one more
massive and game-changing criticism of
all these studies that I'd like to
address because it will change your
perspective on how to think about what
we've just been over and our takeaways
that we'll get to shortly. I'd like to
address that next, but keep in mind that
I'm trying to keep these videos shorter
based on feedback. So, I have a much
more detailed analysis going over
low-carb cancer relationship, the
cardiovascular disease relationship, if
age plays a factor, physical activity,
and more. That is in an extended
analysis that's available for the
Physionic Insiders along with an
accompanying article and all these
lovely perks right here like a regular
podcast with actionable takeaways, live
sessions with me and the rest of the
Insider community, and more. If you're
interested, the link to join is in the
description box. Now, let's get back to
your regularly scheduled programming.
You know how we've been going on about
low-carbohydrate studies? I mean, you
see the titles, right?
The thing is, none of these analyses are
in low-carbohydrate diets like you're
probably thinking of them. For example,
this analysis, the lowest carbohydrate
group is 46% of their nutrition was
carbohydrates.
Some analyses went lower than that, but
none get close to what most people in
the low-carb community would consider
low-carbohydrate. In fact, even in this
study that used the word ketogenic diet,
the most suitable low-carbohydrate diet
seems to have included as much as 100 g
of carbohydrates by my admittedly rough
calculations. Now, I don't know about
you, but that ain't no ketogenic diet on
any planet that I've inhabited, and I've
inhabited many. To be honest, either the
messaging needs to change like this
study title which uses the word lower
rather than low, which is a relative
term and correct, or the researchers
just need to get a lot more granular
with their data. That, of course,
assumes that we have long-term data and
people consuming less than 20 or 10 or
5% of their nutrition from
carbohydrates. I really don't know.
I would also like to point out that all
these studies often compare against
higher-carbohydrate diets of varying
quality. The comparison matters because
the relationship with mortality will
hinge on what you're comparing against.
Another great example is when these
lower-carbohydrate diets indicate some
animal proteins and fats track with a
reduced mortality risk with
lower-carbohydrate diets, yet that's
compared against groups consuming more
of these animal proteins and fats. So,
what would happen when comparing it the
lowest group in these studies to, I
don't know, vegans or vegetarians? I
don't think that we'll get those answers
because
uh where are you going to find enough
people who are mostly or fully
plant-based who are also using a
low-carbohydrate diet? I don't think
that the odds are looking uh too good.
The overall point I'm making is that
even though there's a lot of data here,
there are limitations, some of which I
can't spend more time on getting into
right now. So,
what I'm trying to say here is that
these studies have massive limitations.
Even so, we can learn a few things that
will have significant influence on how
we adopt a healthy low-carb diet. Here's
the bottom line.
One, while these studies don't look at
low-carbohydrate diets like most people
use them, they still give us valuable
information on the trend. As in, if you
reduce your carbohydrate consumption,
how should you go about doing that?
Number two, even if point one is true,
we can't say any of this definitively
applies to people on a true ketogenic
diet because these individuals tend to
have a uh different physiological state
that deserves its own study. Number
three, those two points stated, a
lower-carbohydrate diet can either raise
mortality risk or reduce it. It depends
on the quality of that
lower-carbohydrate diet. So, let's
discuss that next.
Four, you can choose to do one of two
things. Ignore all the data here and
dismiss it as just not applicable to a
true low-carbohydrate diet apart from
possibly a ketogenic diet.
I don't think that's reasonable. My
guess, and it's just that, an educated
guess, is that these trends would scale
even at lower-carbohydrate diets more in
line with what people think of as
low-carb.
Or two, accept the trends in the data.
Basically, if you go low-carb, some
animal-based food is fine. The best
analysis that I went over indicated
around 12% of calories from animal
proteins. That's 60 g on a 2,000 calorie
diet. That number will increase if your
metabolism is higher. And beyond that,
de-emphasizing saturated fats while
emphasizing unsaturated fats as well as
making sure to fit plant-based foods in
the mix. So, here's a list of the foods
that would be plant-based but high in
unsaturated fats.
And a final point on a food choices to
slant your lower carbohydrate diet to be
in line with reduced mortality, making
sure that you consume higher quality
carbohydrates with the little bit of
carbohydrate allotment that you have. If
any,
things like these, especially fiber-rich
sources where possible. And five,
finally just know that there's a lot to
still collect data on and refine. So,
this isn't the end-all, be-all analysis,
but it's the conservative conclusions
that we can make based on the current
literature, acknowledging its
limitations. And if you're looking for
more low-carb content, I've got some
right here going over more analyses, and
I hope to speak with you over there.
Thanks for hanging out. Bye.